<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Git Hub Test Site</title>
    <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio" />
    <updated>2023-11-03T23:26:36-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Mike McGuire</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Getting Started With Indoor Training</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/getting-started-with-indoor-training/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/getting-started-with-indoor-training/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/000-Getting-Started-With-Indoor-Training-2.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Training"/>
            <category term="Equipment"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:26:19-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/000-Getting-Started-With-Indoor-Training-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    According to my Strava data, last season I did my first gravel ride on April 8th, and my first MTB&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/000-Getting-Started-With-Indoor-Training-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p style="text-align: center;">According to my Strava data, last season I did my first gravel ride on April 8<sup>th</sup>, and my first MTB ride on April 21<sup>st</sup>.  So if you start training in early January, that gives about 12 weeks of pre-season prep.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Why do indoor training?</strong></p>
<p>Without getting technical, bike fitness is not maintained when you are not riding. Any riding in the off-season is good for you, but when you reduce your activity, your cardiovascular and metabolic systems both relax, often significantly.   Muscular detraining happens in as little as 2 weeks, meaning that often what you gained over months of riding in the summer is essentially lost, and you’re back to almost square one when you start your next riding season.  (You can check out this <a title="Cycling Science Article" href="https://www.wattkg.com/cycling-science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">W/KG article i</a>f you want to learn more).  But you already knew that because your first rides often feel really hard and strenuous.  You may have also gained some mass over the past few months.  It happens.  And while there are great benefits to cross-training and doing other winter specific activities, your cycling specific physiological skills are not necessarily being maintained.</p>
<p>Riding indoors is efficient, easy, and can provide a lot of benefits depending on how you approach it.  Some of us ride all winter on fatbikes which is also a great way to log hours riding and maintain different elements of your riding skills.  But for most people to maintain and improve cardiovascular and muscular strength, riding on the trainer with a plan will yield better and faster results.  And it's much easier to squeeze in a 1 hour ride every second or third evening in your basement.</p>
<p>Whatever you’ve been up to, if you plan on being bike-fit for the start of the season, you should consider doing some indoor training to get ready.</p>
<p>12 weeks is a perfect amount of time.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Doesn’t indoor training really suck?</strong></p>
<p>Not that long ago, cycling training often consisted of long hours on a stationary bike or rollers at moderate levels of work.  Heart rate was the way to track and guide effort.  For a lot of people, it was boring.  Too boring for many.  But now we have smart trainers and virtual ride worlds and devices that measure and report power output rather than body strain as heart rate.  There is a wide variety of software available and some of it is amazing!  Real coaches have planned it all and almost anyone can follow it to success.  Zwift is a virtual environment with hundreds of thousands of other virtual riders and many courses and road loops.  It has been a game changer for many people.  So, even if you once tried indoor training and hated it, now is a good time to take another look.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="615" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/913-THUMBNAIL-Indoor-Training-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h3><strong>How to get started</strong></h3>
<p>There are a few ways to approach this.</p>
<p>Any time you spin in the off season is good time.  If you are brand new to indoor training and want to learn some fundamentals, you could go to a spin class put on by your local bike store.  You could go to spin classes once a week, which is social, gets you on the bike and will help you learn some technique, but once a week is not enough training to make much difference to your body. Ideally you need to ride 3 times a week to maintain and build, which is where an indoor trainer at your home comes in handy.</p>
<p>You have to find a set up that is moderately enjoyable to ride indoors for 45-90 minutes at a time.  (I’ll talk about equipment and how much this costs later)  A stationary trainer that holds or replaces your rear wheel provides the most flexibility in how you can train.  Because the stand holds you and your bike upright, you can focus on spinning smoothly, your intensity, how high your heart rate is, and other training aspects during your indoor session.  And you can ride slowly if you are recovering without worrying about falling over. </p>
<p>Once you find a place to setup and add some equipment, you can start riding. You can spin while listening to music or watching Netflix at low intensity, or you can find spinning class videos, such as <a title="Spinervals" href="https://www.spinervals.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spinervals</a>, online or on YouTube and follow along.  This is an easy and accessible place to start.  If or when you decide you want to see greater benefits with your training, then you want to look at an online training program with structured training.  Online software like <a title="Trainer Road" href="https://www.trainerroad.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trainer Road </a>or <a title="Zwift" href="https://zwift.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zwift </a>is easy to use, effective, and even fun.   I highly recommend jumping right into structured training.  You can also read about <a title="ndoor training with Zwift was a game changer for me" href="https://www.rideottawa.com/blogs/news/indoor-training-with-zwift-was-a-game-changer-for-me" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how Zwift completely changed Sandra's outlook on indoor training</a>.</p>
<p>There are a lot of programs available to help you train.  Right now, for most people, I’d say the best structured training programs are <a title="Zwift" href="https://zwift.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zwift </a> or <a title="Trainer Road" href="https://www.trainerroad.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trainer Road</a>.  <a title="Sufferfest" href="https://thesufferfest.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sufferfest</a> is also a great option, but it is oriented a little more to serious cyclists and is harder training overall with longer and more frequent workouts in each training plan.  The only free app out there these days is the Kurt Kinetic Fit app (Android &amp; iOS) which has a decent selection of basic workouts.  For more options, you can check out <a title="DC Rainmaker Software App Guide" href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com/2020/03/cycling-indoor-trainer-app-guide.html/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DC Rainmakers Software App Guide.</a>  You could also hire a coach, or plan out, organize and complete structured training manually, without software, but it takes a lot of knowledge end effort for most people.  Training software lets you jump right into it.</p>
<p>Trainer Road has a lot of program variety and is moderate to hard for most people.  Zwift might be the friendliest and easiest program to start training with, and has hard programs for hammerheads too.  In every program, workouts are designed as a plan that structures your time on the trainer for maximum gain.  Novice programs are 3 (sometimes 4) sessions a week. (I typically do 3 structured days a week with extra indoor and outdoor rides)  Most workouts are 60-90 minutes, although you can select shorter ones if you are time crunched.   Each software gives you power targets based on an initial fitness test and on-screen instructions that tell you how to ride. Your equipment displays your power in the software and you adjust your intensity to achieve your targets.  Rides area sequenced and the software tells you when to do them, so you don’t try to do too much.  Rest days are important.  If this sounds complicated, it isn’t really.  The coaches behind each software have done all the thinking and planning for you.  You just need to figure out how much you are going to train each week, for how long, and at what style.   Riding your trainer 3 times a week will help your conditioning a lot and prepare you to start next season strong.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; float: none;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="1080" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/902-Trainer-Road-Or-Zwift-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h3><strong>Which software is better?</strong></h3>
<p><strong>Zwift ($18.99/m) or Trainer Road ($14.99/m)?</strong></p>
<p>For me, I like hard workouts and I like to be focussed.  <a title="Trainer Road" href="https://www.trainerroad.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trainer Road</a> is highly structured training with detailed plans and a lot of plan options, such as 3, 5 or 7 days a week of training over 6, 8 or 12 weeks, and a huge library of workouts.  Most workouts also have shorter (and longer) variants so you can adjust the duration to match your available time.  It is very empirical, and graph based.  No fancy graphics.  Just you and the numbers and coach Chad's on-screen text instructions.  Some people find this intimidating or boring.  I like it because it's clear and concise.  The software controls the trainer resistance during workouts, so when it tells you to pedal hard, you have to pedal hard, and you can’t get away with much slacking.  But it also works really well with many regular, inexpensive trainers using a feature called “virtual power”.  I used Trainer Road for 3 years on a standard Kurt Kinetic fluid trainer with virtual power by simply changing gears manually and adjusting my cadence to match the target power.  This is effective and relatively cheap.</p>
<p><a title="Zwift" href="https://zwift.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zwift</a> is a virtual riding and racing world with graphics and hills and a social component that also has structured training plans.  It’s basically a road bike video game where you ride around with other people.  You can actually do group rides, join race teams, and do other special ride events.  It can really help pass the trainer time with fun visuals, on-screen encouragement, and an experience that simulates riding outside with uphills and downhills and even drafting other riders.  It has a lot of game elements that are designed to keep riders engaged and promote fun.  And it has structured training plans and workouts too, although not quite as extensive as other programs.  Zwift has a lot of variety and seems to be really good for many people, especially people new to online training.  People seem to stick with their training plan which is really important. (really, really, important)  If you have an electronic trainer, Zwift controls the resistance to simulate hills, wind, road bumpiness and it works really well.  Zwift also runs with virtual power which is very effective when doing their structured workouts.</p>
<p>Most online software is similarly priced from $9.99 to $18.99 per month.  Many programs allow you to turn-off payment when you are not using it during the summer, so if you start in January and stop at the end of April, your total cost for Zwift would be $75.96.  Less than one massage.  You can also consider this cost versus a monthly gym or cross-fit membership.  I pay annually for Trainer Road ($99.00) because I use it in the summer too, and I pay monthly for Zwift for the winter months.  Both are definitely worth the price to me.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>What equipment do you need?</strong></h3>
<p>Indoor trainers have been around for a while.  For most people, a trainer that holds your back wheel like setup #1 below is ideal for any and all training.  If you want to do power based training using online software, there are 2 equipment setups that you can consider, setup #2 (lower cost) and #3 (expensive) below.</p>
<h4><strong>Setup #1: Classic Trainer ($50.00 - $250.00)</strong></h4>
<p>A stationary trainer provides great flexibility in how you can train.  If you are just interested in spinning your legs while following YouTube spin-class videos, almost any trainer will work.  You should be able to buy something used for $50.00 - $100.00 online.  New non-smart trainers can still run up to $350.00.  A used Kurt Kinetic or CycleOps Fluid trainer for $150.00 is a great deal.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/900-Classic-Trainer.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="338" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/900-Classic-Trainer-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/900-Classic-Trainer-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/900-Classic-Trainer-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/900-Classic-Trainer-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/900-Classic-Trainer-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h4><strong>Setup #2: Speed &amp; Cadence Sensor + Classic Trainer ($100.00 - $600.00)</strong></h4>
<p>The simplest and cheapest way to start training using power targets is to add speed and cadence sensors to your bike and buy a classic trainer that is suited for <a title="Trainer Road Virtual Power" href="https://www.trainerroad.com/virtual-power" target="_blank" rel="noopener">virtual power.</a>  Your online software will use the data from the speed sensor to determine you power while you turn the cranks.  It works very well for our purposes of training.  Trainer Road and Zwift both have lists of supported trainers so you can <a title="Trainer Road Virtual Power" href="https://www.trainerroad.com/virtual-power" target="_blank" rel="noopener">check to see if a particular model will work</a>.  If you can, stick to Kurt Kinetic, CycleOps, Blackburn and Tacx trainers.  You can often find some of these trainers used for $99.00 online.  Again, a used Kurt Kinetic or CycleOps Fluid trainer for $150.00 is a great deal.  Because there are new smart trainers starting around $500.00 these days, I probably wouldn’t recommend buying a new classic trainer for more than $250.00.  You are better off to find a cheap used one and save up for a smart one.</p>
<p>For sensors, I recommend the <a title="Wahoo Cycling Sensors" href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/bike-sensors" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wahoo RPM Speed and RPM Cadence sensors </a>which you can buy for about $60.00 each.  I’m a big Wahoo fan and these small pods are easy to install and move between bikes. But there are lots of other comparable speed and cadence sensors that work well too such as Garmin sensors which should also be available at your local bike store.</p>
<p><strong>What if you already have a power meter on your bike?</strong></p>
<p>It's also worth mentioning that if you do have an actual power meter on your bike, you can use almost any classic trainer and software without using virtual power, since the power meter will measure and transmit your output.  This is one of the most accurate ways to train with power.  And while a true wheel, crank or pedal based power meter works on your bike both indoors and outside and can provide a lot of training value, the cost of this equipment and the required accessories is quite high, although it can be less than a smart trainer.  There is also some additional complexity and you need to make upgrades to your bike, so I don't advise this direction for riders just getting started unless you are planning to train seriously for competition.   But, for athletes already invested, you already have the necessary equipment and the transition to power based indoor training should be pretty straight forward.  <a title="DC Rainmaker Site" href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DC Rainmaker is my favourite site </a>for detailed information about all things power related.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="338" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/901-Classic-Trainer-Combo-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Setup #3: Smart Trainer ($600.00 - $2,000.00)</strong></h4>
<p>Just to be clear, setup #2 above can be a 100% effective training setup for just about anyone.  Investing in more expensive equipment can get you more accurate measurements for power and other metrics, and it can change the riding experience, but the fundamental theory and practice is exactly the same, so the potential training benefits are essentially the same.  Smart trainers open up additional training opportunities and efficiencies, but that comes with a high cost. </p>
<p>Since 2016, the smart trainer market has exploded and there are a lot of options available for purchase.  There are many online reviews, and probably the most detailed and comprehensive reviews are from <a title="DC Rainmaker" href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com/2020/11/smart-cycle-trainer-recommendations-guide-winter.html/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DC Rainmaker</a> and <a title="GP Lamam Trainer Reviews" href="https://gplama.blogspot.com/p/indoor-trainer-guide-gplama.html?m=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GP Lama</a>.</p>
<p>This is a product most people should buy from your local bike store to make sure that you have some support for setup, and warranty.  If your favourite shop doesn't have trainers or sensors in stock, they can order everything you need.</p>
<p>And another smart thing to do is buy your trainer using a credit card that offers extended warranty protection.  My American Express doubles the manufacturer’s warranty which give you a little extra protection in case something goes wrong with your unit.</p>
<p>Wahoo and Tacx trainers are probably the best products in the smart trainer category.  I’m a Wahoo fan.  Both companies make smart trainers that use your rear wheel, and trainers that replace your rear wheel.  Both types work well.</p>
<p>If you can afford it, get a wheel-off trainer for best performance and feel.  I have a 2018 Wahoo 4<sup>th</sup>generation Kickr ($1699.00) and I love it.  The other trainer I considered was the Tacx Neo ($1899.00) but I prefer the feel of the Kickr.  The best value in this category is the Wahoo Kickr CORE ($1199.00) which has a slightly smaller flywheel than the Kickr, and slightly lower maximum resistance which, for practical purposes, is not a limiting factor for normal humans.  Both brands universally connect to every type of device and software.  As I said, I prefer Wahoo but both are amazing and Tacx has some additional unique features for advanced training.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/910-Wahoo-Kickr-Smart-Trainer-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>On-Wheel trainers are also really good and less expensive.  They are slightly less accurate and have slightly lower maximum resistance ratings, but unless you are over 90kg, super strong, or get very serious about the accuracy of your metrics and training, on-wheel smart trainers are great too.  One benefit to on-wheel trainers is that it's easier to switch bikes, which makes it good for sharing with someone else.  For on-wheel trainers, the Wahoo Kickr Snap ($799.00) is my pick.  It has universal connectivity like the Kickr and great maximum resistance for its price.  (You only need to add a cadence sensor since it does not ship with one)  The Tacx Genius trainer is the equivalent product at slightly higher in price, with slightly higher resistance.  There are also less expensive Tacx on-wheel models with good reviews.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="450" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/911-Wahoo-Kickr-Snap-Smart-Trainer-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<p>I will also add that Wahoo updated all their product designs in 2018 and as of late January 2019, there are some known and ongoing product issues which they are dealing with.  My experiences dealing direct with Wahoo Customer Support have been amazing and I remain a Wahooligan fanboy.  Tacx also has some known issues, and I have heard mixed reviews on custom service through their distributors.  In any case, if you purchased this product from your local bike store, they should be able to help out with warranty issues.  (So support your Local Bike Store when you can!)</p>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>What else do you need? </strong></h3>
<h4><strong>A Laptop, Tablet, Phone, AppleTV, and maybe a TV or M</strong><strong>onitor</strong></h4>
<p>The trainer and sensors need to talk to your choice of software so you need a laptop, iPad, tablet, phone or AppleTV (for Zwift) connected to the internet for this purpose.  The main difference using any device is the size of the screen and where you can position it while you are riding.  You need to be able to see and read the on-screen instructions during your workout.  Trainer Road has well designed apps that show the target numbers and graph clearly and it works fine on a phone sized screen.  Zwift is essentially a video game, so a bigger screen provides a more immersive experience.  Zwift on an iPad is pretty good.  On a 40” TV it’s really good.  And If you have an Apple TV or Chromecast device, you can stream your tablet or phone on to your TV to get a bigger image.  You probably don’t need a 40” TV for Trainer Road, but I like it anyway.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that when your partner also trains with Zwift, who gets to use the big TV during co-training sessions becomes important.  It doesn't matter who purchased the TV, it automatically became a "Relationship TV" once installed in your shared training space, and you will need to work out a suitable sharing methodology.  This is also true for shared Bluetooth speakers and music selection during the training session.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; float: none;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="185" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/903-Phone-Tablet-Laptop-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h4><strong>Bluetooth LE or Ant+ Wireless ($20.00) on your devices</strong></h4>
<p>If you are using a Macbook, iPad or iPhone, your trainer and sensors will connect using Bluetooth so you don’t need anything extra.  Android phones are usually good with Bluetooth LE, but Android tablets are hit-and-miss, so you need to test connections using the sensor setup app to make sure everything works.  </p>
<p>ANT+ is a different way to connect training devices wirelessly but must be added to your laptop.  You may need an <a title="ANT+ USB Dongle on Amazon.ca" href="https://www.amazon.ca/Anself-Forerunner-Compatible-CycleOps-TrainerRoad/dp/B01MDS60Y1/ref=sr_1_2_sspa?crid=2DTL4SRK8PF4X&amp;dchild=1&amp;keywords=ant%2B+dongle&amp;qid=1607346010&amp;s=electronics&amp;sprefix=Ant%2B%2Celectronics%2C193&amp;sr=1-2-spons&amp;psc=1&amp;spLa=ZW5jcnlwdGVkUXVhbGlmaWVyPUEyVlk0STYxVDBHT0haJmVuY3J5cHRlZElkPUEwNTYxNDQ3MUE1MUVVS0lZSEE3JmVuY3J5cHRlZEFkSWQ9QTEwMDE2MDIyRUdYUjlaRURXWVBVJndpZGdldE5hbWU9c3BfYXRmJmFjdGlvbj1jbGlja1JlZGlyZWN0JmRvTm90TG9nQ2xpY2s9dHJ1ZQ==" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ANT+ USB dongle</a> to connect your trainer and sensors.  Most PC's do not have the correct type of Bluetooth so you will need to add the ANT+ USB device.  Some software on Mac's will only use ANT+ to read sensors, so you may also need it on a Mac.  If you are using Zwift you don’t need the ANT+ dongle because they have a Companion phone app that will handle the connections and transmit them to your laptop via the internet.</p>
<p>Connecting everything is not as hard as it might seem, but it could take 15 to 30 minutes depending on your level of digital savvy, so just don’t expect to hop on your new gear and start Zwifting 5 minutes after you unpack it. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="margin-top: 25px; margin-bottom: 25px; float: none;" src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="753" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need-xs.jpg 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need-sm.jpg 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need-md.jpg 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need-lg.jpg 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/3/responsive/904-What-Else-Do-You-Need-xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<h4><strong>Heart Rate Monitor ($60.00)</strong></h4>
<p>More data is better for training.  Trust us, it is.  If you don’t have one, get a heart rate monitor so you can see the strain on your body during workouts.  You can also wear it on your outdoor rides and record the heart rate data in Strava to see how your body is working on those rides too.  It’s easy to learn about heart rate zones online and it helps you to understand your physical limits during exercise.  If you have a health tracker or FitBit and it broadcasts heart rate as Bluetooth, that will usually work with training software too.  If you are going to buy a monitor, I like the <a title="Wahoo Tickr Heart Rate Monitor" href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/heart-rate-monitors/wahoo-tickr-heart-rate-strap" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wahoo Tickr</a>.  Chest strap monitors are generally considered more accurate than other types, but get something.</p>
<h4><strong>A Trainer Specific Tire ($40.00 - $60.00)</strong></h4>
<p>Several manufacturers make tires specifically for use on indoor trainers.  These tires are harder than regular tires and last longer. They are also supposed to be quieter. If you are using a mountain bike for you training, you will need a smooth tire or trainer tire, but if you are just starting out with a road bike, you don’t necessarily need one.  You will wear out your regular road tire though, so you will have to buy something at some point.</p>
<h4><strong>A Strong Fan ($20.00 - $200.00)</strong></h4>
<p>Make sure you have a fan that can cool you down.  You will need it.  If it has a remote control, even better.  (because you will forget to turn it on and start your workout)  This adjustable <a title="Stanley Blower Fan" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07YKXF9VC/ref=cm_sw_em_r_mt_dp_THIZFbQ27WVG7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Blower model </a>by Lasko is so strong we only run it on the lowest setting. A <a title="Remote on off switch" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07GXCYWRQ/ref=cm_sw_em_r_mt_dp_hMIZFbHNEWEJE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">remote On/Off switch</a> is also handy because you will start riding and forget to turn the fan on.   We also have a fancy <a title="Wahoo Blower Fan" href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/accessories/kickr-headwind-bluetooth-fan-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wahoo Headwind fan</a> that can automatically adjust itself based on your heart rate or cadence or power.  It’s cool, but I really only use the remote control app.  You can get 2 of the blower fans and remotes for less.  Anything you already have will work to start.</p>
<h4><strong>A Training Log (Free)</strong></h4>
<p>You’re going to be working hard and you will eventually want to examine your progress and accomplishments from your training.  I suggest you immediately start tracking your efforts by linking <a title="Strava" href="https://www.strava.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Strava</a> to your training software to keep track of everything. You can sign up for a free account and then link your training software.  Trainer Road and Zwift will automatically share your data with Strava so you can keep a record of everything.  A free Strava account is sufficient for this purpose, but you can pay for premium features to help you analyze the data.  Other more complex analytics programs, like <a title="Golden Cheetah" href="https://www.goldencheetah.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Golden Cheetah</a>, will import your historic data from Strava if you decide you want more powerful analytics, so just start using Strava and you are set-up for future tools.</p>
<hr>
<h3><strong>Wow.</strong></h3>
<p>So that is a lot of information.  It’s not really that hard to get started, but between equipment, sensors, and software there are bunch of different things to purchase and piece together.  This post highlights what has worked for us over the last 5 years and continues to work well.</p>
<p>If you are still not sure about jumping in, Sandra describes her experiences in this post, "<a title="Indoor training with Zwift was a game changer for me" href="https://www.rideottawa.com/blogs/news/indoor-training-with-zwift-was-a-game-changer-for-me">Indoor training with Zwift was a game changer for me!</a>".  Take a look.</p>
<p>We also have a private <a title="Ottawa Indoor Training and Riding Group" href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/OttawaIndoorTraining/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Facebook Training Group</a> where we share ideas and training specific interests and ask each other questions about what is working.  This has given us some great insight in how to start training and keep training through the off-season.  If you decide to get into indoor training, you can join too.</p>
<p><a title="Subscribe to the Ride Ottawa Newsletter" href="http://eepurl.com/dyZepT" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Subscribe to the Ride Ottawa Newsletter</a> to receive our regular monthly newsletter and blog updates.  (and course and event notifications)</p>
<p>You have 12 weeks before riding season is in full swing.<br>Make the most of it</p>
<hr>
<h3><strong>Links:</strong> (opens in new window)</h3>
<p>More about power based training setups on the Trainer Road Blog:<br><a title="Trainer Road Power Based setups" href="https://blog.trainerroad.com/popular-indoor-power-based-training-setups/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trainer Road - Power Based Training Setups</a></p>
<p><a href="https://blog.trainerroad.com/popular-indoor-power-based-training-setups/"></a>Wahoo guide to indoor trainers:<br><a title="Wahoo Guide To Indoor Trainers" href="https://blog.wahoofitness.com/beginners-guide-indoor-bike-trainers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">All About Indoor Trainers</a></p>
<p>For more details about Virtual Power and specific trainers:<br><a title="Trainer Road - Virtual Power" href="https://www.trainerroad.com/virtual-power" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trainer Road - Virtual Power</a><br><a title="Zwift - Virtual Power" href="https://zwift.com/hardware#ready" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zwift - Virtual Power</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Trainer Review Sites:<br><a title="DC Rainmaker" href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">DC Rainmaker<br></a><a title="GP Lamam Trainer Reviews" href="https://gplama.blogspot.com/p/indoor-trainer-guide-gplama.html?m=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GP Lama</a>.  </p>
<p>Sensors:<br><a title="Wahoo Bike Sensors" href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/bike-sensors" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wahoo Bike Sensors<br></a><a title="Wahoo HR Monitors" href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/heart-rate-monitors/wahoo-tickr-heart-rate-strap" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wahoo Heart Rate Monitors</a><br><a href="https://www.wahoofitness.com/devices/bike-sensors"><br></a>My favourite powerful and cheap blower fan:<br><a title="Lasko Blower Fan" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07YKXF9VC/ref=cm_sw_em_r_mt_dp_GPIZFbG4F8S4D" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lasko Blower Fan</a></p>
<p>ANT+ USB Dongles:<br><a title="ANT+ USB Module" href="https://www.amazon.ca/Anself-Forerunner-Compatible-CycleOps-TrainerRoad/dp/B01MDS60Y1/ref=sr_1_2_sspa?crid=2DTL4SRK8PF4X&amp;dchild=1&amp;keywords=ant%2B+dongle&amp;qid=1607346010&amp;s=electronics&amp;sprefix=Ant%2B%2Celectronics%2C193&amp;sr=1-2-spons&amp;psc=1&amp;spLa=ZW5jcnlwdGVkUXVhbGlmaWVyPUEyVlk0STYxVDBHT0haJmVuY3J5cHRlZElkPUEwNTYxNDQ3MUE1MUVVS0lZSEE3JmVuY3J5cHRlZEFkSWQ9QTEwMDE2MDIyRUdYUjlaRURXWVBVJndpZGdldE5hbWU9c3BfYXRmJmFjdGlvbj1jbGlja1JlZGlyZWN0JmRvTm90TG9nQ2xpY2s9dHJ1ZQ==" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Buy on Amazon.ca</a><br><a href="https://www.amazon.ca/dp/B06XKCXFVV/ref=cm_sw_r_cp_apa_i_p15qCbRDPV7KY?fbclid=IwAR0vkofDw35VJu5JjhZtTtTjDqg382Ze5wea2TlGH5L4pdPLvidlrGe4udA"></a> </p>
<hr>
<p style="float: left;"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Indoor training with Zwift is a game changer!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/indoor-training-with-zwift-was-a-game-changer-for-me/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/indoor-training-with-zwift-was-a-game-changer-for-me/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/906-Zwift-Game-Changer.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="Zwift"/>
            <category term="Training"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:26:36-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/906-Zwift-Game-Changer.webp" alt="Sandra in her pain cave" />
                    When I mention to friends that I am going to ride my trainer in the basement, often their response is:&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/906-Zwift-Game-Changer.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Sandra in her pain cave" /></p>
                <p>When I mention to friends that I am going to ride my trainer in the basement, often their response is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="align-center">“Really, it sounds so boring?"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, it can be boring until you find out what works for you.  It took me 3 years to get a system in place that I liked.  Now I don’t just like it, I look forward to the regular exercise and fitness gains. There are still some days that I groan about getting on the trainer, but 20 minutes in my mood has changed and I’m glad I did it.  It is space efficient too, you don’t need a lot of space to get started.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2.webp" alt="" width="1024" height="576" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/responsive/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2-xs.webp 384w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/responsive/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2-sm.webp 600w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/responsive/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2-md.webp 768w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/responsive/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2-lg.webp 1200w ,https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/14/responsive/906-Zwift-Game-Changer-2-xl.webp 1600w"></figure>
<p><strong>Why train indoors?</strong></p>
<p>For some of you this will be the big question.  I train because I want to maintain my fitness over the winter so that I feel strong when mountain bike season starts in the spring.  Riding is much more fun for me when I feel fit.  When climbing every hill feels like a struggle, it is less fun.</p>
<p><span lang="EN">Riding indoors on a trainer is also very time efficient.  It is a great workout that only takes about 5 minutes of pre-ride prep, versus loading up the car and packing up clothes, snacks, etc.  </span><span lang="EN"><span lang="EN">After a long drive home from work, sometimes I just don’t feel like getting back in my car again. During the school year, I also don’t enjoy cleaning my bike, it just adds onto my to-do list.</span></span></p>
<h3><strong>How did I get started?</strong></h3>
<p><span lang="EN">3 years ago I bought a $100 used trainer online, set up my road bike on it, and started spinning to free online videos.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  It got my legs moving, but </span>didn't really feel like training.  </span><span lang="EN">I had to guess all the time about how much power I was using and also how fast my cadence was.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span></span><span lang="EN"><span lang="EN">I hated it and barely noticed any impact on my fitness.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span></span></span></p>
<p><span lang="EN">2 years ago, I bought a Wahoo Kicr Snap on-wheel smart trainer.  (<a title="Wahoo Fitness" href="www.wahoofitness.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">www.wahoofitness.com</a>)  It's one of the least expensive ways to get into the Smart Trainer scene.  Smart trainers have built-in power meters and they can control how hard it is to pedal. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"> I added a cadence sensor and a heart rate monitor so I could see every aspect of my training on-screen.  <br></span></span></p>
<p><span lang="EN">What a difference with a power reading, cadence sensor and heart rate monitor.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I’m a numbers geek and loved to look at my heart rate on different rides.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I signed up for Trainer Road, (www.trainerroad.com) a grueling training program that a lot of racer-types use.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I loved it and hated it all at the same time, but I decided that the workout intensity was too much for me.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>Often 40 minutes into a workout I was struggling to keep my legs spinning, and the last 20 minutes was horrible.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>So horrible, I dreaded every single ride, because there never seemed to be an easy workout, even though I was doing their easiest training plan. </span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="display: block; float: none; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/Zwift-Workout-Screen_1024x1024.jpg?v=1546532660" alt="Zwift Structured Workout" width="1024" height="560" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3><!--StartFragment--><span lang="EN"><strong>What about that Zwift thing?</strong><br></span></h3>
<p><span lang="EN">In late February 2018, I tried another online training program called Zwift (http://zwift.com/).<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I kept seeing a lot of my Strava friends using it, so I thought it must be OK.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>It was.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>Zwift is an online, virtual cycling world with thousands of other riders, many different riding worlds, races, group rides, and it's own structured training workouts.  Right away, I loved the visual distraction it offered.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I loved that some routes go by big old growth forests, through volcanoes, into London and around Central Park in New York City.</span></p>
<p><span lang="EN">I also mentally find it so much easier, because it is structured with both easy and hard workouts, and all of them are doable for me.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>Even if I get on my bike tired, or stressed out, or sore from the day before.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>I’ve finished all of my planned workouts without feeling like I’m going to explode at the end.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>There is a good selection of training plans too, and I like that a professional has done the thinking for me.</span></p>
<p><span lang="EN">This year I’ve selected the “Gravel Grinder” plan because I want to do some longer gravel rides, and maybe a couple of races.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>Plus, it is most similar to mountain biking compared to the other specialized road biking plans.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">   </span> </span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/Zwift-Training-Plans_1024x1024.jpg?v=1546532645" alt="Zwift Structured Programs" width="1024" height="576" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<!--StartFragment-->
<h3><strong> Did I mention you can race too?</strong></h3>
<p><span lang="EN">In March 2018, just before our annual mountain bike trip to Utah, I stumbled upon a fun Zwift racing team.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">   </span>So after I got home, still smiling about the desert sun and feeling WAY less motivated to train, I decided to try a Zwift Race.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>It was crazy hard!<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>But crazy fun!<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>It’s a little hard to explain, but something everyone should try.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>There are 4 categories in each race (A, B, C, D),  each category has a mass start, and then you ride around the course, chasing other people and trying to draft other riders.  The mini-battles that ensue are stellar.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">   </span>It’s incredibly challenging being well-matched with another racer and having to battle for an hour, giving it your all to the finish.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span>And you might come third last in your category, but it doesn’t matter because you have pushed yourself.  And there are detailed statistics to look at and geek out on through the Zwift Power Race site (<u><span style="color: #1155cc;"><a href="http://www.zwiftpower.com"><span style="color: #1155cc;">www.zwiftpower.com</span></a></span></u>).<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  For me, i</span>t has been a good way to measure my training progress.  And I think it's pretty cool to race with riders from all over the world.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><br></span></span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/Zwift-Training-Plan-fondo_1024x1024.jpg?v=1546532580" alt="Zwift Strucured Workouts" width="1024" height="576" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p> </p>
<p><span lang="EN">This year the races draw about 300 riders each week, but there is a lack of women which I think is unfortunate.  It concerns me that women only make up 1-3% of the participants and I think it would be great to get more of us doing these races.  Theses races are for all fitness levels, are easy to join and are an incredibly good workout.  If you've ever wanted to try racing but haven't, Zwift is an easy and cool way to start right in your own basement. </span></p>
<h3><strong>How much is it?</strong></h3>
<p><span lang="EN">If you’ve been curious about Zwift, it is great to do in the off season.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span></span><span lang="EN">Ask around and you will probably find others who use it and many people enjoy it for the groups rides.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">  </span></span><span lang="EN">The monthly subscription is $18.99, which is much more affordable than a gym membership, and even cheaper then just one group spin class.  To get started you need an indoor trainer, a few bike sensors and a laptop or tablet.  You can start with a used dumb trainer, or buy a more advanced smart trainer if you want to jump-in with both feet.</span></p>
<p><span lang="EN">Our next blog post will be about what equipment you can use to get started.   </span><span lang="EN"><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">And we have a closed, novice indoor riding group on Facebook that you can join (</span></span><span lang="EN"><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><a style="color: #3b5998; cursor: pointer; text-decoration: none; font-family: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, '.SFNSText-Regular', sans-serif; font-size: 13px; font-style: normal; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: auto; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: auto; word-spacing: 0px; -webkit-text-size-adjust: auto; -webkit-text-stroke-width: 0px;" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/OttawaIndoorTraining/">https://www.facebook.com/groups/OttawaIndoorTraining/</a>), where you can ask questions and follow other like-minded cyclists.</span></span></p>
<p><span lang="EN"><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">Zwift is a</span> great option if you are looking to build your general fitness in the off-season without any particular training in mind, and it also has structured training programs that you can try if you're ready to a bit more serious about riding better.  <br><br>But most of all for me, it's super fun.</span> <br><span lang="EN">She is based in Ottawa, Canada.<br></span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Preparedness, Control &amp; Performance</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/preparedness-control-and-performance-psychological-aspects-of-mountain-biking/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/preparedness-control-and-performance-psychological-aspects-of-mountain-biking/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/4/BF3568A3-7564-45EF-A078-12101BCC2CB6.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Training"/>
            <category term="Skills"/>
            <category term="Mountain_Bike"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T22:47:38-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/4/BF3568A3-7564-45EF-A078-12101BCC2CB6.png" alt="" />
                    A few years ago, I read and article on a prominent MTB blog that said, “if you’r’e crashing, you’re learning.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/4/BF3568A3-7564-45EF-A078-12101BCC2CB6.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">A few years ago, I read and article on a prominent MTB blog that said, “if you’r’e crashing, you’re learning.  It’s a necessary part of becoming a better mountain biker.”</span></p>
<h3 class="p1" style="text-align: center;"><span class="s1">Here’s the thing.  </span><span class="s2">It isn’t necessary at all.  </span></h3>
<hr>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Mainly those are words of comfort offered by friends to someone who has crashed, or used by someone who crashes regularly and uses this mental approach as an excuse for their inability to keep rubber side down on a trail. Suppressing your fear of crashing and just accepting it will happen so you can try and huck off bigger things is not how professional athletes seek improvements.  This cliché implies you will get better as a rider if you just throw yourself at bigger stuff on harder terrain. This is not a good strategy for most people and often it ends with a moderate to severe injury, lots of time off the bike and increased fear or riding.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s2">The idea that you need to crash to improve is totally incorrect.</span><span class="s1"> If downhill ski racer had to crash repeatedly in order to get better and faster every season, they would never make it to an Olympic level.  A ski crash is often a career ending knee injury.  For skiers, strength training and repetition (lots of repetition) on specific manageable ski runs are the formula for practice and improvement.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<div style="text-align: center;"><figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/IMG_9350_1024x1024.jpg?v=1683162005" alt="Controlled terrain for better learning" width="702" height="527" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></div>
<h3 class="p1 align-left" style="text-align: center;"><span class="s2">The Right Conditions For Learning </span></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Your unconscious brain is always trying to protect you.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>Anytime the ancient animal inside you is threatened, the brain floods your body with adrenaline and other chemicals to help you act.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>Fear is a main trigger for this resulting SURVIVAL MODE.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>As an instructor, it’s my job to create and manage the right conditions for students to succeed in lessons.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The correct conditions for safe and effective learning do not put an athlete into SURVIVAL MODE.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>In this amped up state an athlete can’t process verbal or visual instruction, loses control over kinesthetics, and can’t successfully experiment and create variations in performance to better understand and feel the skills they are practicing.  </span><span class="s2">Riding beyond your ability and trying to survive is not a good methodology for MTB improvement. </span><span class="s1"> How can you learn a trail and remember details bombing down at full-speed? Even if you manage to ride or survive a particular feature after failed attempts, how will you know what you did that made the difference?  What did you change?  How much? What was the timing?  How will you repeat it I order to build muscle memory if you don’t know what adjustments you made?  It’s impossible to reliably repeat skills if they were done through unconscious instinct and were not intentional.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">As an instructor, I will tell you that if you are crashing, then something is missing in your skill set.  It could be many things.  Riders crash when they are not combining skills well for particular trails or features, often when they are tired.  Experienced riders make mistakes too, and in my own experience, they tend to be significant because they are traveling at higher speeds, on steep or more technical terrain, where the forces acting on the bike and rider are much higher.  A pedal strike at low speed is uncomfortable; a pedal strike at 20km/h results in the bike immediately riding off the ground, one or both tires losing grip and a significant rotational force around the pedal spinning the bike.  It is almost impossible to recovery.  It’s much safer to practice new cornering skills in a parking lot until you get a sense of the required movements and timing before taking it to the trail. A controlled environment allows for safe and more effective learning.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>Once we’ve practiced and processed, we can head to a section of trail and apply the skills and techniques and refine further.</span></p>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/IMG_9631_1024x1024.jpg?v=1683162166" alt="Challenging Terrain" data-is-external-image="true"></div>
<h3 class="p1" style="text-align: center;">Up for a challenge, or under threat?</h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">There is a decent body of sport psychology research that deals with the emotional states of athletes and how they affect performance.  The short version is; Feeling CHALLENGED can be good.  Feeling THREATENED is not.  Athletes who believe they do not have the resources to cope with stressful encounters in sports events focus on what could potentially go wrong, are considered to have a ‘threat’ mentality.  They also have elevated cardiovascular responses to the treat condition triggered by adrenaline which have negative impacts on response times and physical output.  Delayed reactions and unresponsive muscles are not good for riding hard features.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Disregarding your gut feelings about safety is not something we encourage during lessons.  Ever.  Fear triggers the threat response.  I use </span><span class="s2">preparedness</span><span class="s1"> to maintain a challenge response, at least most of the time.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/IMG_2074_1024x1024.jpg?v=1683162235" alt="Preparing for a big MTB ride in Pemberton" data-is-external-image="true"></p>
<h3 class="p1" style="text-align: center;"><span class="s2">Emotional &amp; mental strength &amp; conditioning</span></h3>
<p class="p1">From the original article, I like the idea of mental preparedness and managing emotions that may hold you back while doing your sport. Fear is a handy and useful emotion that can save your butt sometimes, and the challenge is to use your thinking brain to compare your preparedness to the risk scenario, and see how your emotional response changes. It’s also very valuable to question WHY you are considering a new feature or risky move. Are your friends “encouraging” you? Do you have something to prove? To who? What are you supposed to do tomorrow? If you fail, what are the consequences? Would it be worth to fail? What would you learn? Or is more practice and preparation a better decision.</p>
<p class="p1">During lessons, we have a “no pressure” philosophy and mantra. We NEVER push anyone to ride terrain or features they are uncomfortable with. We always try to say, “If you’re not feeling it, this [rock, roll, jump, whatever] will be here next time”. Riders that choose to bypass or walk risky features are safe people to go on bike trips with. “Know your limits” is a real thing.</p>
<p class="p1">Feeling prepared and confident is the key for me when I want to attempt bigger trails or features. Personally, this comes to me through repetition, variation, and visualization.</p>
<p class="p1"><strong>Repetition</strong> trains muscles for specific movements, builds muscle memory so you can repeat the movements without thinking, conditions your eyes and brain to see and understand what is happening, and establishes the foundation for timing of moves.</p>
<p class="p1"><strong>Variation</strong> is the process of practicing skills at faster and slower speeds, on different degrees and steepness of terrain, and in different weather and trail conditions in order to adapt the skills from practice so we can use them on any trail in any terrain or conditions.</p>
<p class="p1">This<strong> preparedness</strong> is what matters to me and gives me confidence. I know that I have practiced the skills, tested them with variation, and I can mentally think of the steps I need to do to succeed.</p>
<p class="p1"><strong>Preparedness</strong> also applies to your riding uniform, safety equipment, bike set-up, trail knowledge, directions and way-finding, and the additional equipment you carry. Manage as much as you can with your equipment to reduce distraction. Building routines to cover off each of these areas can go a long way to adding confidence to your ride.</p>
<p> </p>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/IMG_8232_1024x1024.jpg?v=1683162314" alt="Grippy rocks and just enough steepness" data-is-external-image="true"></div>
<h3 class="p1" style="text-align: center;"><span class="s2">More skills practice on green or blue trails</span></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Riders need a solid foundation of skills including body position, movement and timing to be able to tackle ever more challenging terrain and features.  You will not achieve this quickly or as effectively simply by riding trails and “just going for it”.  Don’t get me wrong here, riding MORE is the key to putting things into practice to make them into habits.  To do maneuvers like drops, you need to practice on controlled and safe terrain which is typically smaller or less gnarly than your desired feature.   </span><span class="s2">Blue trails, not black.</span><span class="s1">  Typically this is smaller drop that can be repeated a bunch of times until you are consistent.  Then you can make small changes in your position, timing, pressure (or whatever) to see what happens.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>But the consequences of getting that new variation wrong are low.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>You practice with variation until you are consistent.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>Then you find the next slightly bigger drop and apply proper form and control to that feature.</span></p>
<div style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/IMG_9502_1024x1024.jpg?v=1683162394" alt="Lots of reps builds skills" data-is-external-image="true"></div>
<h3 class="p1" style="text-align: center;"><span class="s2">Wrap-up</span></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">You may crash when you’re biking.  It’s not a sign that you are getting better, especially if you keep doing it.  Mental preparedness and control is part of becoming a better athlete.  As an instructor, I believe that learning foundation skills and then more complex maneuvers<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>in controlled conditions helps leads to better mental preparedness.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>This creates better conditions for learning new skills and experimenting, and additional practice and refinement leads to greater control because you will be able to apply your skills across more variable conditions.  More control ultimately leads to more performance; and that might mean more speed, bigger drops, or just more fun.</span></p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Midsummer&#x27;s Bikepacking Trip</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/a-midsummers-bikepacking-trip/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/a-midsummers-bikepacking-trip/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/19/909-Summer-Bikepack.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="Travel"/>
            <category term="Bikepacking"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:09:48-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/19/909-Summer-Bikepack.webp" alt="Summer Bikepack Trip" />
                    I recently went on a 3-day solo bike packing trip and wants to share what I did to help prepare&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/19/909-Summer-Bikepack.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Summer Bikepack Trip" /></p>
                <p>I recently went on a 3-day solo bike packing trip and wants to share what I did to help prepare for your next bike packing adventure.  Read below to find out how I got my <a title="Kona Honzo CR" href="https://www.konaworld.com/honzo_cr.cfm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new Kona Honzo</a> ready, what equipment and food I packed, and how i packed it and carried it. </p>
<p>It was a trip I thought about doing for 2 years and finally decided to do this summer.  Just to get away from everything for a few nights.  I left from our house in Ottawa, biked to Lac Phillippe in Gatineau Park, Quebec via Chelsea, and spent a second night camping at Lac Taylor before returning home.</p>
<p>It really isn’t as hardcore, scary or intimidating as you think it is!  The full story of my adventure will be posted on the <a title="Komna Cog Blog" href="http://cog.konaworld.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kona Cog Blog</a> soon.  You can read more about my trip and check out the other great stories too.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1950-Sandra-1_grande.jpg?v=1567183196" alt="Sandra B Bikepacking Trip" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p>Want to know more about our adventure-girl ?  Check out these links:<br><a title="Kona Ambassador Sandra Beaubien" href="https://www.konaworld.com/team_Sandra_Beaubien.cfm">https://www.konaworld.com/team_Sandra_Beaubien.cfm<br></a><a title="More about Sandra Beaubien" href="https://spark.adobe.com/page/N2peSfkq9VxtK/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://spark.adobe.com/page/N2peSfkq9VxtK/</a></p>
<hr>
<h3>Bike Preparation</h3>
<p>There are a few simple and relatively inexpensive things you can do to help get your bike ready to make the bikepacking experience as enjoyable as possible. </p>
<h3>Front Chanring</h3>
<p>If you plan on long days in the saddle or expect a lot of hills, your gearing needs to be easy to help manage the extra load and weight on your bike.  This means adding some easier gearing.  The easiest and cheapest way to do this is change your front chainring to a SMALLER one.  Front chainrings are measured by the number of teeth they have.  My <a title="Kona Honzo CR" href="https://www.konaworld.com/honzo_cr.cfm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kona Honzo CR</a>, came with a 1x11 drivetrain with a 32 tooth front ring (32t).  I got <a title="Full Cycle Ottawa" href="https://www.fullcycle.ca" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Full Cycle</a> to install a 30 tooth front ring (30t)  for me to make it easier to pedal in the easiest gear and this made a HUGE difference!  I could keep a faster cadence for the entire first day, which meant my legs did not burn out as quickly, and when the hills were steep I could keep pedalling so I didn't have to walk anything.  The extra weight on the bike is really felt on the climbs and at the end of the day!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1951-Smaller-Chainring_grande.JPG?v=1567019592" alt="Get a smaller chainring for your bikepacking trip" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Frame Tape</h3>
<p>With some rain in the forecast on my trip, and having learned from previous trips, bike packing bags, especially the frame bag, can get grit and gravel under the velcro straps and this can leave a lot of scratches on your bike.  Since this was my Honzo’s first bike packing adventure, I took the time and put clear helicopter tape under the velcro straps.  It took me a good hour (realistically, maybe 2 hours) but my frame is still in mint condition.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1952-Helicopter-Tape_grande.JPG?v=1567019676" alt="Protect your frame with helicopter tape" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<hr>
<h3><br>Packing Tips</h3>
<p>This by no means is an expert list of what to bring on a 3-day solo trip, think about it as “this is what Sandra took and survived”.</p>
<h3>Food</h3>
<p>Bring extra food.  You will eat it all.  The calorie consumption while bike packing is huge.  I have no scientific evidence, but I can guarantee after day 1 you will be hungry almost all the time.  I chose to bring dehydrated meals to save weight since I was on my own.  I did learn that 2-year-old dehydrated food does not taste very good.  It tasted great 2 years ago, but it certainly has a shelf life.  But I was hungry enough to eat it.  An old backpacking habit I have is to plan on eating something hot and salty when you get into camp.  For me, this is a package of Mr. Noodles.  Not a solid nutritional meal, but it is a quick and easy snack to get some instant calories, warm liquid and salt into your system.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1953-Food-For-3-Days_grande.JPG?v=1567019723" alt="Bikepacking food for 3 datys" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Clothing</h3>
<p>It is really easy to overpack clothes on a bikepacking trip.  Accept the fact that 3 hours into day 1 your riding gear will be stinky, but it won’t really get any <em>stinkier</em>, so you might as well wear the same shirt, outer shorts, and socks 3 days in a row.  I brought 2 bike short liners, which worked well, and one base layer to wear in case it was cold riding.  I made sure to have dry clothes including quick dry pants, a sweater, base layer, and warm socks to wear at camp and to bed.  I brought 2 sports bras, one to ride in and one clean one to wear at camp.  I brought underwear, but I can never seem to find it when I am changing at camp anyway, so I will re-think that for next time. 😊</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1954-My-Clothing_grande.JPG?v=1567019773" alt="Bikepack clothing for 3 days" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Little things</h3>
<p>Be very careful of all the cute little things you can buy and bring with you on a trip, those clever little things you think you can’t live without for 3 days.  These little things can quickly add pounds of weight and take up a lot of limited bag volume and you most likely won’t use them.  Below is a picture of my “little things”, all of which are functional items primarily for warmth and comfort based on past trips,  and not just because they are “cute”.  Save your toothpaste samples from your dentist because they are perfect for trips like this. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1955B-The-Little-Things-You-Bring_grande.JPG?v=1567019922" alt="Little things you bring bikeapacking" width="450" height="600" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Bike tools</h3>
<p>I brought the minimum amount of tool that I felt I could get away with.  When I was packing the night before I felt like I should have more, but I brought what I knew how to use and I figured I could have been rescued by Mike if needed.  But you will need at least one inner tube, tire lever, a pump, a multitool, and I brought a lock, just to be safe.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1956-Necessary-Bike-Tools_grande.JPG?v=1567019983" alt="Essential tools to bring bikepacking" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Cooking supplies</h3>
<p>Keep it simple when bikepacking.  You don’t need any cute little cooking utensils or espresso machines.  They add up to a lot of weight and space very quickly.  I know I need tea and warm food at least once a day, so bikepacking without a stove is not an option for me.  My cup nests in my bowl, and all my little things fit inside my cup.  The Jetboil stove we use is perfect for boiling water for tea and re-hydrating food.  One spork is usually what I carry.  And a small knife.  I always bring matches and fire starter as a back up.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1957-Cooking-Supplies_grande.JPG?v=1567020052" alt="My bikepack cooking equipment" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Toiletries</h3>
<p>Minimal supplies is best.  It is easy to overpack these items. but you need some essentials.  I bring a variety of painkillers and antihistamines in one bottle.  Other than my glasses, contacts and small mirror to put my contacts in, you just need things to brush your teeth and wash your hands.  The pocket soap is great for this.  Kleenex and TP are, well, essential.  Don't expect any campsite to have Charmin in the outhouse.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1959-Toiletries_grande.JPG?v=1567020091" alt="Bikepack toiletries" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Miscellaneous</h3>
<p>A thin rain jacket for summer bike packing is awesome and essential.  Small, lightweight but important to stay dry if you get stuck out in a thunderstorm, and it adds a lot of warmth in the wind or in the evening.  I like sandals at camp so I don’t have to hang out in my stinky bike shoes after a day of riding, and a book is a must for me.  I bring a USB charging battery pack that allows for 5 charges of my phone since it is my essential tool for navigation and emergencies.  I brought a real camera to save the battery life of my phone and had a first aid kit. (not shown in the picture)  Those long rubber NiteEyez twist ties are for emergencies, in case something breaks on one of my bags and I need to strap things back together.  Also not pictured is a spare dry bag which is really important to keep things dry when the weather turns against you.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1960-Miscellaneous-Things_grande.jpg?v=1567020169" alt="Miscellaneous things to bring bikepacking" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Sleeping Gear</h3>
<p>This is by far the heaviest and bulkiest of everything I bring.  I use a hammock, with special straps, and a specific hammock tarp for sleeping.  I used an under quilt that goes under the hammock for the first time this trip, but I think I prefer sleeping on a Thermarest under me in my hammock.  My sleeping bag is a lighter 5-degree summer weight bag and borderline warm enough, but I ALWAYS pack a down jacket that I can use when sleeping or as needed on the trip.  I also bring a beanie to sleep in.   I always keep my head warm when sleeping outside. 😊</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1961-Sleeping-Kit_grande.JPG?v=1567020215" alt="Bikepacking sleep gear" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<h3>Packing</h3>
<p>I always think everything won’t fit in my bikepacking bags but it always does.  I often have to change where I put things in each bag but eventually, I get everything where I want it.  I have a designated packing room, and Mike took a picture of my as I was jamming things into a dry bag, but like magic it all fit on my bike!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1962-Packing-My-Gear_grande.jpeg?v=1567020263" alt="Packing up all my bikepacking gear" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p> And here is what Honzo looked like all packed up and ready to go!</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none; margin-top: 20px; margin-bottom: 20px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/1963-Packed-Up-And-Ready_grande.JPG?v=1567020303" alt="Bikepacking gear all ready to go on my bike" width="600" height="450" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p>As I said, this is what worked for me on a solo trip. I know more serious bike packers take less stuff than me, and others might take more stuff, but this is what kept me going for my 3 day trip to Gatineau Park and back.</p>
<p>I hope this gives you some ideas about doing your own trips and how to start organizing gear and food.</p>
<p>The full story of my adventure will be posted on the <a title="Komna Cog Blog" href="http://cog.konaworld.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kona Cog Blog</a> soon.</p>
<p>Have fun out there !</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What I Have Learned Switching From Clipless to Flat Pedals</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/what-i-have-learned-switching-from-clipless-to-flat-pedals/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/what-i-have-learned-switching-from-clipless-to-flat-pedals/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/20/911-Flat-Pedals.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mountain_Bike"/>
            <category term="Equipment"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:26:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/20/911-Flat-Pedals.jpg" alt="Switching to flat pedals" />
                     A few weeks ago, James Wilson (www.bikejames.com) revisited an old post of his about industry stereotypes and pedals. Specifically in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/20/911-Flat-Pedals.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Switching to flat pedals" /></p>
                <p data-offset-key="ejd5g-0-0" data-editor="fdbsv" data-block="true"> <span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">A few weeks ago, <a title="Bike James Website" href="https://www.bikejames.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">James  Wilson (www.bikejames.com)</a> revisited an old post of his about industry stereotypes and pedals.  Specifically <a title="Pedal Lies" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/clipless-pedals-are-not-the-problem-the-lies-told-to-sell-them-are/#comment-261074" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in this post,</a> he criticizes why the bike industry, and many bike riders, are so bullish on clipless pedals.  </span>James writes a lot of posts that challenge conventional or historic MTB theory, and while I'm not always a huge fan of everything of his, the dude is an accomplished coach and trainer and does put in a lot of time questioning the status quo and looking at how so called "norms" apply to normal riders.  James also markets and sells his own flat pedals, so he is pretty committed to his point of view.  You can decide for yourself what to take and what to leave from his writings. Also, I searched for comparative articles that discuss the benefits of clipless pedals and there is very little online that says anything other than "you can pull up for a smoother stroke" (which James debunks in the manifesto) or "thats what the pro's use so just get used to them".  Or lots of marketing spiel.</p>
<p data-offset-key="ejd5g-0-0" data-editor="fdbsv" data-block="true">Writing this post I came across James’ <a title="Bike James' Flat Pedal Revolution" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/the-flat-pedal-revolution-manifesto-how-to-improve-your-riding-with-flat-pedals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bike James' Flat Pedal Revolution</a> manifesto which covers off many of his arguments and findings in detail and is worth a read.  It seems to me that I have pretty much been doing what he suggests in his manifesto.  My personal observations and notes are written below.</p>
<p data-offset-key="ejd5g-0-0" data-editor="fdbsv" data-block="true">I still like my clipless pedals a lot, and I am a supporter of any MTB material that helps riders to make informed choices about what works best for them.  This includes fact based studies (rare), intelligent and informed opinions by people in the bike or fitness industries (somewhat rare), a occasionally thoughts and descriptions by my favourite racers or personalities (because I LIKE Greg Minaar and I think Seth works hard to learn).<img loading="lazy" style="float: none; margin-top: 50px; margin-bottom: 50px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/001_grande.jpg?v=1564366017" alt="" width="NaN" height="NaN" data-is-external-image="true"></p>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="7f1bp-0-0"><span data-offset-key="7f1bp-0-0">I have been mountain biking since 1986.  The first real mountain bike I purchased was a 21" Nishiki and it came with pretty crappy "bear-trap" flat pedals.  They hard very little grip so we bolted plastic toe cages with shoe straps on the front to hold our shoes in place.  These clips and straps came directly from the road bike world.  And they sucked.  It was hard to get your foot into the pedal, and even harder to get you foot out in a hurry.  They sucked, but we were riding.  Then in 1991, Shimano came out with SPD clipless pedals which had a recessed cleat that still allowed you to walk when needed.  (because you would be walking sometimes.  They really changed the MTB world and </span><span data-offset-key="7f1bp-0-0">I switched from crappy bear-trap pedals and toe cages to SPD's.  I have ridden SPD's ever since. Until May 2019.</span></div>
<p class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0"><span data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0">I have been working on my MTB certification to advance to the next level, and I have to be able to do certain skills well such as jumping.   I have always been a mediocre jumper and weak on drops over a few feet high.  So, I needed to improve myself.  I know, in theory, what I am supposed to do when jumping and dropping, but have never felt very stable or solid.</span></p>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0"><span data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0">So, just like we do when we are woking with clients, I reviewed and broke down my essentials skills and I decided that a few things needed to improve to reach my goals.  TIMING was the weak aspect of these maneuvers for me.  I never really rode DH where many, if not most, people use flat pedals and really learn to jump well. When I did DH it was using SPD's, and this got me thinking that my technique may be compromised because I am doing things clipped in that are not correct, or at least not well executed. I did not WANT to ride flat pedals, but I decided to switch in an effort to improve my techniques. I have been recording my experiences and I have also been closely watching clients all season to verify if this was just me, or if some things might apply to others too.</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" style="text-align: center;" data-offset-key="d4lf8-0-0"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none; margin-top: 50px; margin-bottom: 50px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/002_grande.jpg?v=1564366279" alt="" data-is-external-image="true"></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="302ea-0-0"><span data-offset-key="302ea-0-0"> </span></div>
<h3 class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">So what have I learned after switching ?</span></h3>
<ol>
<li class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"><span data-offset-key="1ci1s-0-0"><strong>Everyone on clipless pedals is cheating.</strong>  Myself and others that I have instructed who uses clipless pedals is pulling up when they execute rear wheel lifts, preloading the bike, or attempting to jump. I don't care how much you try to execute a proper preload by compressing through the crank and exploding off the pedals, you will also lift your feet as a reaction to the action. This is not necessarily the end of the world, but i’d say this makes everyone with clipless pedals lazy. This results in poor technique and by that, I mean many, if not all, clipless riders will only preload with ½ the necessary force because they end up lifting to achieve height. Most riders are using a too-slow, artificial lift using their legs to raise the rear wheel instead of using their legs to compress down into the trail, explode up and then control the resulting forces. This is bad and affects your ability to drop, lift either or both wheels, manual, and bunnyhop. So, a lot of important trail moves are compromised. Flat pedals provide a much larger and effective platform to compress with; more area for your foot and shoe to push against equates to better power transfer and bike loading. Once I switched I realized just how small the cleat interface on your clipless shoe and pedal is, and how much power is being lost into my shoe when compressing.  And I tested this with different clipless shoes too.  Even super-stiff, uncomfortable shoes are not doing much to help this scenario. After I switched to flat pedals and shoes and watched video of myself, this was obvious to me. Correcting this alone has substantially improved my jumping and drop mechanics. This is the #1 reason to switch to and practice on flats.</span></li>
<li data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"> <strong>My climbing performance is NOT compromised because of flat pedals. </strong> I would say that anyone using good body position, hovering and standing techniques will likely be just as good climbing anything on flat pedals.  My clipless pedals do provide more clearance over rocks and other trail obstacles than my RaceFace Atlas flats, so timing pedal strokes and using ratcheting are more important on techy climbs and in rock gardens than with clipless pedals and shoes.  If you don't have those skills, then switching to flats at first seems to make climbing harder.  But I think may riders are compensating for medicore technique when using clipless.  I am PR'ing my favourite climbs on flats.  The biomechanics, if not the same, are not less effective, just different.  On technical terrain a lot of riders LIFT their rear wheel when climbing over obstacles which is a learned technique and can be effective, but success is easily restored using improvements in body position and hovering or standing in place of lifting, which I will argue are better, correct techniques you can apply in more situations. Hey, lift using your feet if it helps you, nothing wrong with that. But if that is your ONLY tool for climbing, then you are limited. Flat pedals require some other mechanics which are worth learning.</li>
<li data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"><strong>Downhill performance is +10x on flats.</strong> Just ask a downhiller.  Flat pedals provide several benefits when descending; better power transfer through your cranks, greater range of foot position and rotation, ease of adjusting heels down, quick and easy removal of your feet from the pedals.  Good body position, range of motion and angulation are maximized with flat pedals. This is why most DH riders are on flats. (Yes, I know the UCI DH riders are mostly on clipless pedals. Professional riders have much better and precise techniques and I'm guessing they work on techniques regularly.  Most riders never work on skills.  Ever.)  I really do like the secure and positive foot placement that clipless pedals give me when I ride rough stuff, mostly because I can be lazy when clipped in overall, but flat pedals allow me to be far more dynamic on my bike which allows me to use greater range of motion and body position for everything. I especially notice how much better I corner on flat pedals.</li>
<li data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"><strong>Safety is better on flats. </strong>Even though I am accustomed to riding difficult features on SPD's, I am discovering that being able to instantly jump off my flat pedals is giving me confidence to try harder lines and maneuvers including jumps and bigger drops (although that is combined with better drop techniques). When practicing manuals, flat pedals are almost mandatory because when you loop-out on a manual, SPD's will not release when you pull back off the pedals and you can end up on your ass in the grass. For practicing manuals alone, get flats. I teach lots of beginner and intermediate riders, and FLAT PEDALS are the single biggest contributor to safely learning and building confidence. EVERYONE remembers the first time they could not clip out and fell over on their bike. This effect results in many crashes on the trail where moving your foot off the pedals could save you from crashing. Crashing is bad and hard and results in a massive loss of confidence for every rider. Just because you have clipless pedals on your road bike is not a reason to put them on your mountain bike.  And don't get clipless pedals for your kids please. Just don’t.</li>
<li data-offset-key="9rm4t-0-0"><strong>Overall efficiency is.....different.</strong> All summer I have been systematically riding my favourite trails. First on clipless (like always) and then on flats. Each time, I feel "better" on flats. Almost every descent is faster, but I'd say it's just more fun all the time. On climbs, the Strava times indicate no difference. NO DIFFERENCE. Sometimes I miss a hard, punchy feature on flats, but this is currently because my timing of pedal stokes is off a touch and I haven't yet adjusted. (It takes a while to unlearn 20 years of clipped in muscle memory) Sometimes your foot gets ‘stripped” off of a flat pedal by a rock or root, which can be unnerving at first. Learning to put your foot back on flat pedal in the correct spot requires some new muscle memory learning too. And flat shoes with pedals are surprisingly sticky and sometimes hard to adjust at speed which is something else to learn. Right now, at the end of my rides, I'd say I feel more tired after riding on flats, but then I've only been on them since May and I suspect some muscle adaptation is in process. And I'm splitting hairs on this. It's really just some calf fatigue I'm feeling. This is really obvious on long XC-ish rides (20km) I'd say there is some greater efficiency in using clipless pedals, but for me it is mostly on longer rides. Overall, for the style of riding I do, I think I am having MORE FUN on flat pedals. (maybe because it is still a little new and I like the challenge)</li>
</ol>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="bs9ej-0-0"><span data-offset-key="bs9ej-0-0"> </span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" style="text-align: center;" data-offset-key="bs9ej-0-0"><img loading="lazy" style="float: none; margin-top: 50px; margin-bottom: 50px;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/004_grande.jpg?v=1564366341" alt="" data-is-external-image="true"></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="bs9ej-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="83jck-0-0"><span data-offset-key="83jck-0-0">Will riding flat pedals make you a better rider?</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="cta5j-0-0"><span data-offset-key="cta5j-0-0"> </span></div>
<p class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"><span data-offset-key="3gone-0-0">No, not necessarily. If you are not interested and open to learning new and proper techniques, then you are likely to hate the differences and resist the need to adapt. If you don't take the time to learn, you might see SOME benefit in terms of confidence, safety, and maybe body dynamics. But you won't necessarily get much improvement. Flat pedals might make you feel like a noob and change where you sit in your pack of friends on weekly rides.</span></p>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"><span data-offset-key="3gone-0-0">You can practice good skills using any pedals and see good results. If you take a lesson (or lessons) you will absolutely be taught better techniques regardless of pedals. I think flat pedals you force you to execute “correctly” during practice and can achieve greater improvement.  Afterwards, if you go back to clipless (I ride about 25% o the time on my SPD's now) your techniques WILL be better.</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"> </div>
<p class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"><span data-offset-key="3gone-0-0">But if you think switching to flats will make you a better rider overnight without any additional effort, it won't. You will need to do 3-5 rides to adapt your basic riding and build flat confidence and techniques. If you are just starting or getting back into riding after some time off, then I’d say, yes, ride flats for a few seasons or forever. It is safer and your confidence will grow quickly.</span></p>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="3gone-0-0"><span data-offset-key="3gone-0-0">If you are into racing, I think clipless pedals can be more efficient; but spending some time on flats and re-learning basic things like body position, cornering, and drops could make a huge difference in your riding. (Nino was a DH rider before he switched to XC competetion btw). Start slow, on moderate trails you know and feel and learn the differences. Get some actual coaching so you can learn good techniques or unlearn bad habits.</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="fa8tn-0-0"><span data-offset-key="fa8tn-0-0"> </span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="figjr-0-0"><span data-offset-key="figjr-0-0">And have fun with it.</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="figjr-0-0"><span data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0">Because bikes are supposed to be fun!</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0"><span data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0">Bike James Links:</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2u6s1-0-0"><a title="Clipless Pedal Lies" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/clipless-pedals-are-not-the-problem-the-lies-told-to-sell-them-are/#comment-261074" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">Clipless-pedals-are-not-the-problem-the-lies-told-to-sell-them-are</span></a>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
<span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"><a title="Pedalling Muscles" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/which-muscles-are-really-used-during-the-pedal-stroke/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Which-muscles-are-really-used-during-the-pedal-stroke</a></span>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
<a title="Clipless Driving Away Riders?" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/is-the-lie-that-you-need-clipless-pedals-driving-away-thousands-of-riders-every-year/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">Are-clipless-pedals-driving-away-thousands-of-riders-every-year?</span></a>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"><a title="Bike James Flat Pedal Manifesto" href="https://www.bikejames.com/strength/the-flat-pedal-revolution-manifesto-how-to-improve-your-riding-with-flat-pedals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">Bike-James-flat-pedal-revolution-manifesto</span></a></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"><br>Looking for more info on cycling techniques?:</span></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"><a title="Flamme Rouge Facsheets" href="http://www.flammerouge.je/factsheets/factsheets.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0">Check out the Flamme Rouge Factsheets (topics in right column)</span></a></div>
<div class="_1mf _1mj" data-offset-key="2q36h-0-0"> </div>
</div>
<p data-offset-key="cr6hu-0-0" data-editor="fdbsv" data-block="true"> </p>
<div class="" data-offset-key="cghic-0-0" data-editor="fdbsv" data-block="true"> </div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Things To Know About Kids Bikes</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/things-to-know-about-kids-bikes/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/things-to-know-about-kids-bikes/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/18/910-Kids-Bikes.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mountain_Bike"/>
            <category term="Equipment"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:13:51-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/18/910-Kids-Bikes.jpg" alt="Things to know about kids bikes" />
                    Content by Chris Wood Being a dad of fledgling cyclists and teaching mountain bike lessons to other people’s kids has&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/18/910-Kids-Bikes.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Things to know about kids bikes" /></p>
                <h4>Content by Chris Wood</h4>
<p>Being a dad of fledgling cyclists and teaching mountain bike lessons to other people’s kids has taught <em>me</em> a lot about how to help kids have fun on a bike. One thing that it has become clear to me is that it‘s not always fear or lack of effort holding kids back from riding well and having fun. Often it's their bikes. Sometimes it’s because the bike needs a tune-up, sometimes it’s the way a bike fits, and sometimes it’s the quality of the bike.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/912-Angualtion-Practice.jpg?v=1560353199" alt="Chris teaching the L'il Rippers angulation at VeloMSM" width="702" height="395" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p>Here's a breakdown of key things that can make-or-break a child's experience on a bike.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Bike Size</strong><br>In order for biking to be fun, kids need bikes that fit their body dimensions. They need to be able to pedal uphill, stand up to go downhill, lean the bike to corner, and resist the bike to stop. A bike has to be the right size, it really is that simple. Two years is typically the longest you can expect a bike to fit a child well. Choosing a bigger size so the bike will stick around longer risks having your child spend a year feeling awkward, out of control and uncomfortable, all the while developing bad habits to overcome the poor fit of the bike. All of these factors can have a negative impact on how much a kid likes to ride. It’s like putting your kids on skis that are too small or too large for them and hoping they can still turn.  Every parent knows how hard it is to balance lifestyle and financial choices.  But if your family is even a little serious about riding bikes together, you'll need to start flipping bikes every year or two, just like hockey and ski gear.  Fit equals fun.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="float: none;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/000-Bike-Sizes.jpg?v=1560355756" alt="Kids Bikes 20, 24, ,26 Inch wheels" width="2400" height="625" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p><strong>Gears</strong></p>
<p>Hang in here with me through this part. It’s a little complicated but important.</p>
<p>Most kids’ bikes come from the manufacturer with gears meant more for the road, but we want your kids out on the trail. Off-road bikes need better shifters and easier gears for pedalling up hills.  Some bikes come with up to 27 gears, (3 x 9 speeds) making shifting confusing for new riders. Single front chain ring gearing called “one-by” is much easier for kids (and adults) to learn. It’s also a little lighter. Front chain rings connected to the pedals with 28-32 teeth are the right range for summer riding.   On the other end of the bike, look for a cassette (that’s the clump of gears on the back wheel) with the largest cog having between 34 and 40 teeth. If you can, avoid rear cassettes with 8 speeds or less as the gearing typically will not be easy enough to allow your child to climb hills on the trails.  If you can get something with 9 or 10 speeds, it is always better.  Some brands like Rocky Mountain and Kona are shipping bikes that offer better gearing and brakes and if you are going to invest in a better ride for your little ripper, we highly suggest you check those two specific brands.</p>
<p>If your eyes glazed over during the last paragraph here is what you need to know. When your child is going to be riding trails and you want them to have the most fun and grow, the perfect gear set up would be a 30 tooth front single chain ring and a 12-40 tooth rear cassette.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>"PUSHING MY BIKE UP THIS HILL IS SO MUCH FUN!"<br></em><em>- Said no child ever</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Brakes</strong><br>Safety and fun are the first priorities on any kids’ lessons with us, and good stoppers are pretty high on the list of priorities when choosing a bike. As pint-sized riders build more trail skills, the ability to control speed becomes increasingly important. If anyone is going to have the confidence to progress and try new skills they need to trust their brakes to stop them. Learning to use and trust equipment builds confidence, and confidence improves learning, which increases fun!</p>
<p>Kids have specific brake challenges because their hands are small and their grip is not as strong as an adult’s.  Brakes need to provide ample stopping power and have levers that can be moved closer to the handlebar to fit shorter fingers. Disc brakes that allow for one-finger braking are the absolute best because then kids can keep all their other fingers on the handlebars for greater steering control. (Same for adults BTW)</p>
<p> </p>
<p>There are three basic styles of brakes.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Coaster brakes.</strong> These work by pedalling backwards and are fantastic for skidding on the sidewalk, but not great for control on the trail. The biomechanics are fundamentally at odds with trail riding.  They are good for very small children on their first bike, learning to ride on pavement, because they are easy to learn. Kids can develop a sense of stopping power and distance as they learn on these simple bikes.<br><br></li>
<li><strong>Linear pull or “V” style brakes.</strong> These brakes squeeze the rim of the wheel to stop. They used to be on all adult bikes too.  There is huge range in quality and cost, but on kids’ bikes they are often cheap and not effective. With less power than disc brakes they are dependent on straight wheel rims as a bent rim causes the brakes to drag on the wheel, affecting how the bike rides.  Pads must be closely aligned to the rim and checked for wear and alignment regularly.  Bikes from reputable bike stores will be set up correctly and should have good stopping power.  Regular adjustment is required.<br><br></li>
<li>
<p><strong>Disc brakes.</strong> These come in two basic styles, cable actuated and hydraulic. Cable actuated disc brakes are less expensive and offer greater stopping power than V-brakes.  Hydraulic disc brakes are the gold standard, just like brakes on adult bikes, with way more stopping power and more adjustment for reach. They are more expensive and found on better kids and youth bikes.<br><br></p>
</li>
</ol>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/000-Brakes-Gears.jpg?v=1560355821" alt="Disc brakes, V-Brakes and Gears" width="2400" height="784" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Brake Setup</strong></p>
<p>As important as brake choice is, brake lever setup is just as important, and it is free! Correct positioning requires moving the levers inwards, along the handlbar, towards the center of the bars, so smaller hands can reach the end of the levers for more leverage.  As your child progresses they will spend more time standing out of the saddle, so levers should also be rotated down to a comfortable angle while standing.  Good levers should be adjustable in terms of distance from the bars (called “reach”), so that small fingers can hook onto the lever at the first and second finger joint. When you buy a bike, insist that the shop sets this up with your child present to test it. If they are unwilling to do this or do not know how, contact us and we’ll arrange for you to meet with one of our partner bike shops who understand the importance of correct bike setup for all riders, including kids.<br><br></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/000-Lever-Reach.jpg?v=1560356531" alt="Adjust Brake Lever Reach" width="2400" height="504" data-is-external-image="true"> </figure>
<div>
<blockquote>
<p><em>"CAN YOU HOLD MY JUICE BOX AND WATCH ME RIDE THS ROCK ROLL..."<br>- Every rider parent's dream</em></p>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div> </div>
<p><strong>Dropper posts<br></strong>Nothing has changed mountain biking more than dropper seat posts in recent years.  Dropper posts allow for changes in seat height with the simple push of a button on the handlebars.  Being able to have the seat all the up allows for full leg extension and powerful pedalling for climbing like any regular bike.  But dropping the seat down and out of the way allows a rider to get low and is safer for going downhill and over obstacles. At this point in time, very few youth bikes come with dropper posts.</p>
<p>Fortunately, they can be added with after-market parts, although they are expensive.  A dropper post with 100mm of travel is plenty for a kid is is probabaly the only size that will fit most kids bike.  If the cost is just too much to stomach, then a good option is to make sure that the bike is equipped with a quick release so that the seat can be lowered and raised manually as needed. This is something you can teach every kid to do by themselves whenever the trail starts to look rough.  In our kids’ clinics, we carry wrenches and Allen keys so we can adjust seats when we do certain exercises.  l wonder how many lawns a kid needs to cut to earn a dropper post?</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/Dropper-Video-Square_grande.gif?v=1560358310" alt="Dropper Post GIF" width="499" height="499" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Suspension <br></strong>Unless you take your kids to Whistler every summer or vacation near a big hill like Mont Ste. Marie, good fit, good gears and good brakes are more important than suspension on a kid’s bike.  And to be clear, low-end bikes from chain stores like Canadian Tire and Wal-Mart are not usually good full-squish bikes.  The cheap, low quality suspension typically found on those bikes is worse than no suspension at all because it adds a lot of weight, cost, maintenance, and usually doesn’t function well.  Quality suspension adds stability and control. If kids are riding trails, front suspension is going to help on bikes with 24” wheels and up. Full suspension is good for rocky trails, but it will make the bike a bit heavier, add significantly to the price, and requires maintenance every season to keep working well.  On bikes with 20” wheels and smaller, you are better off budgeting for better brakes, gears and more ice cream on rides if you want your child to really like bike rides.</p>
<p>That said, there are some pretty sick kids bikes being offered now from Rocky Mountain, Kona, Spawn and some other boutique companies.  If you are serious about a full suspension rig for your little athlete, we highly recommend you purchase one through your bike store.  Just like adult bikes, these are complex, performance machines that must be assembled and adjusted correctly before you hit the trails, and they will require regular service every year to keep them running well for maximum fun.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/000-Kids-Suspension.jpg?v=1560356867" alt="Kids Full Suspension Bikes" width="2400" height="535" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“CHEAP STUFF BREAKS”<br></em><em>- My son</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sigh. Kids break things, and lose things, and since we have to feed them EVERY day, they grow out of things. Quality kids’ bikes purchased from and set up by bike shops are built to last and need less maintenance than department store bikes. Take care of a good youth bike and you will be able to sell it in two years when your child outgrows and recover a lot of the original cost. If you sell the bike for a few hundred less than you paid for it, that is the same amount of money that you would have spent on a department store bike that could suck most of the joy out of mountain biking for your child.  Some of our partner bike stores even have buy-back programs and lists of parents looking for used bikes.  If you are the parent of a young ski racer, you are probably familiar with these programs and how they work.  Give your Local Bike Store a call and ask them if they can help you out.  Some stores are now offering kids demo bikes for rent and trial.</p>
<p>As a father of two there are few things that make me happier than seeing my kids have fun on bikes, because if I can see them having fun on bikes it likely means I’m riding too. This is part of my definition of quality parenting and is not to be confused with goofing off.</p>
<p>Many things go into helping your children find joy in riding. The choice of trails, the pace, good snacks (never underestimate the power of a well-timed gummi-bear stop), your attitude, and the equipment they use all play into determining if the day ends in tears, or high fives and fist bumps. And when they say, “Can we ride again tomorrow?” you get to say "Yes!", like it wasn’t your idea all along.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>We hope this little guide helps to clarify what makes a good kids bike.<br>As always, feel free to email us with any questions.  And we are always happy to introduce you to bike stores that we know can set you up with appropriate, quality products.</p>
<p><strong>Links to other resources:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a title="Singletracks - 2018 10 best kids bikes" href="https://www.singletracks.com/blog/mtb-gear/10-best-kids-mountain-bikes-2018/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Singletracks' 10 Best Kids bikes of 2018</a></li>
<li><a title="Rascal Rides - Best Kids Bike Brands" href="https://rascalrides.com/best-kids-mountain-bikes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rascal Rides - Best Kids Bike Brands</a></li>
<li><a title="Cycle Sprog - How to buy a kids bike" href="http://www.cyclesprog.co.uk/bikes/buying-a-kids-mountain-bike/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cycle Sprog - How to buy a kids bike</a></li>
<li><a title="2 Wheel Tots How to Choose a Kids Bike" href="https://www.twowheelingtots.com/how-to-choose-kids-pedal-bikes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2 Wheel Tots - How to choose a kids bike</a></li>
</ul>
<p style="float: left;"><span lang="EN"><br></span><span lang="EN">He is based in Ottawa, Canada.<br></span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What You Need To Carry When You Ride</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/what-you-need-to-carry-when-you-ride/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/what-you-need-to-carry-when-you-ride/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/17/908-Cover-Whats-In-That-Pack.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Mountain_Bike"/>
            <category term="Equipment"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T23:02:14-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/17/908-Cover-Whats-In-That-Pack.png" alt="What You Need To Carry When You Ride" />
                    Funny things happen when you teach groups of 10 year old mountain bikers. Like when they find out after 2&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/17/908-Cover-Whats-In-That-Pack.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="What You Need To Carry When You Ride" /></p>
                <p>Funny things happen when you teach groups of 10 year old mountain bikers. Like when they find out after 2 hours of riding that you're hoarding a huge bag of gummy bears in your pack. And they hatch a plan to distract you and loot your pack for the candy, but then end up being fascinated by all the stuff you're carrying.</p>
<p>Then you get questions like, "What's all that stuff for?".  If you're wondering what instructors carry in their packs, on and off lesson, here's my gear.</p>
<p><br>
<script id="asp-embed-script" data-zindex="1000000" type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page-embed.js"></script>
<a href="https://spark.adobe.com/page/Lm18jjxiF6kj8/" class="asp-embed-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" style="width: 100%;" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page/Lm18jjxiF6kj8/embed.jpg?buster=1545018464744" alt="My Page" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ottawa-Gatineau Fatbike Trail Primer</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/ottawa-gatineau-fatbike-trail-primer/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/ottawa-gatineau-fatbike-trail-primer/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/15/907-Fatbike-Trail-Primer.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Trails"/>
            <category term="Fatbike"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T22:46:32-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/15/907-Fatbike-Trail-Primer.png" alt="" />
                    Fatbiking has come a long way in the Ottawa-Gatineau region in 5 years. We have an abundance of machine and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/15/907-Fatbike-Trail-Primer.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Fatbiking has come a long way in the Ottawa-Gatineau region in 5 years.  We have an abundance of machine and foot groomed trails to ride with new riding areas beign added every season.  This primer is due for an update but still has lot if good intel.</p>
<p>
<script id="asp-embed-script" data-zindex="1000000" type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page-embed.js"></script>
<a href="https://spark.adobe.com/page/AzlCy3ysfgZGN/" class="asp-embed-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" style="width: 100%;" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page/AzlCy3ysfgZGN/embed.jpg?buster=1545018597136" alt="Ottawa Gatineau Fatbike Trail Primer" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Fatbike Tire Pressures</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/fatbike-tire-pressures/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/fatbike-tire-pressures/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/13/905-Fatbike-Tire-Pressure.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Fatbike"/>
            <category term="Equipment"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T22:16:29-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/13/905-Fatbike-Tire-Pressure.jpg" alt="Fatbike Tire Pressure" />
                    When you're out in the variable conditons of winter tire pressure can make-or-break a ride. Fatbiking is still pretty new&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/13/905-Fatbike-Tire-Pressure.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Fatbike Tire Pressure" /></p>
                <p>When you're out in the variable conditons of winter tire pressure can make-or-break a ride.  Fatbiking is still pretty new to many people and it takes os trial and error to dial-in your grip.  Check out our guide to getting your tires dialled for different conditions.</p>
<p><br>
<script id="asp-embed-script" data-zindex="1000000" type="text/javascript" charset="utf-8" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page-embed.js"></script>
<a href="https://spark.adobe.com/page/ccbNTPbsUYMX7/" class="asp-embed-link" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img loading="lazy" style="width: 100%;" src="https://spark.adobe.com/page/ccbNTPbsUYMX7/embed.jpg?buster=1545018566232" alt="GO LOW" border="0" data-is-external-image="true"></a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Better Energy Drink Recipie</title>
        <author>
            <name>Mike McGuire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/a-better-energy-drink-recipie/index.html"/>
        <id>https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/a-better-energy-drink-recipie/index.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/11/903-Energy-Drink-Recipie.webp" medium="image" />
            <category term="Training"/>
            <category term="All Articles"/>

        <updated>2023-11-03T21:52:40-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/11/903-Energy-Drink-Recipie.webp" alt="" />
                    This past season starting in early summer, I started getting pretty strong leg cramps in the middle of the night.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://mcguirems.github.io/portfolio/media/posts/11/903-Energy-Drink-Recipie.webp" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0103/1362/9754/files/Ride-Ottawa-Hyrdration-Drink-800x.jpg" alt="" data-is-external-image="true"></figure>
<p>This past season starting in early summer, I started getting pretty strong leg cramps in the middle of the night.  I was riding a lot, almost every day, but not long distances.  My trainer rides were some of my hardest rides.  And when I was outside on the bike, I never wanted any food.  No Larabars, no gels, and minimal water.  Indoors on the trainer I would drink 2 water bottle hours and hour and half session, but I never ate anything.</p>
<p>Since the cramps were really disrupting my sleep, I did some ‘research’ to figure out what I should do to change things up.  I looked at "nutrition" overall, and specifically about during-ride and post-ride and on-ride nutrition to determine what could help.  The Trainer Road Blog is an excellent repository of bike and racing knowledge and from there I was able to ask The Google some relevant questions and find some guidelines about on-biike nutrition and performance.  The short answer for me is more carbs during and immediately after riding, more salt, and no alcohol after.  So</p>
<p>So now I'm trying to be disciplined by eating and drinking nutrition during rides and immediately after rides.  For every hour on the bike, I eat half a Larabar or 3 to 5 Cliff Blocks, 250ml of water.  If it's a long ride or multiple rides, I try to add 1/4 bottle of the recipe below.  After every ERG trainer session or ride i consume 500ml of  Mikeade, up to 1L if I feel I need it.</p>
<p>This is the third variation of the same ingredients I have made and it feels right.  I reduced the initial amount of sugar and Maple Syrup (for potassium!).  Overall an all-natural, fairly thick, not too sweet, high carbohydrate fruit drink, with no chemical taste.  It stays mixed and does not separate.  It's best to mix a few liters at a time and drink within 2 weeks, like regular juices.</p>
<p>Shop around for juice on sale. (Walmart, Loblaws). Order Trace Mineral Drops online. Use high quality fine Bailene Sea Salt or similar. Way more effective than Gatorade or Zero Water, cheaper than a high-end drink mix. </p>
<p>I've had no more cramps since I started making and drinking this.</p>
<p><br><strong>Ride Ottawa Recovery Drink:</strong></p>
<p>Ingredients:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 cups coconut water</li>
<li>1 cup pineapple juicer</li>
<li>1 cup orange juice</li>
<li>4 cups water</li>
<li>1/4 coconut sugar</li>
<li>1/4 maple syrup</li>
<li>1/4 cup honey</li>
<li>4 teaspoons high quality sea salt</li>
<li>2 tablespoons Trace Mineral drops</li>
</ul>
<p>Directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Mix juices together in the proportions shown above.</li>
<li>Leave some space in the top of your jug</li>
<li>Add coconut sugar, maple syrup, and honey.</li>
<li>Shake well 50 times, then salt, and Trace Minerals.</li>
<li>Shake another 50 times.</li>
<li>Chill in fridge.</li>
<li>Drink 250ml per 1 hour during workout.</li>
<li>Drink 500ml immediately after workout.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
